DIANYI LIU



HIGHLIGHTS

A curious researcher in Plant Science.

A talented bench worker that designs and conducts sophisticated experiments.

A passionate pop science translator that brings the world's ideas and knowledge into Mandarin Chinese.

A fun chaser enjoying dancing, bodybuilding, painting, and learning languages for the quality of life.

TECHNIQUES AND SPECIALIZATIONS

Specialization

Genetics, Cell Biology, Molecular Biology, Microscopy, Microbial Biology, Plant Biology Cell Size Control, Mitosis, Multiple Fission Chlamydomonas, Volvocine Algae, Cell Synchronization, Retinoblastoma Tumor Suppressor Pathway

Languages

Mandarin Chinese - Native Language
English - Professional Working Language
Japanese - Intermediate/Advanced Level - Japanese Language Proficiency Test, Level 2 (日本語能力試験 N2)

Statistics and Data Analysis

National Scholarship, Tier 1, Year of 2010 National Scholarship, Tier 2, Year of 2009

R Programming for data joining and data manipulation including statistics fundamentals (data analysis, correlation, regression, and inference) and data visualization (using packages ggplot2, base R, and lattice)

EDUCATION

University of Missouri, St. Louis. MO Ph.D. Candidate in Cell and Molecular Biology	2015.8 - Present GPA 4.0/4.0
Washington University, St. Louis, MO M.S. in Plant and Microbial Biology	2012.8 - 2015.5
Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY B.S. in Biology, Developmental Genetics Specialization Graduated with Honors in Biology Irwin Oster Award, Excellence in Genetics Research Outstanding Undergraduate Achievement, Developmental Genetics Specialization	2010.8 - 2012.5
Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China B.S. in Biology	2008.9 - 2010.6

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Thesis Research 2012.8 - Present

Dr. James Umen's lab. Donald Danforth Plant Science Center

Thesis: Elucidating the cell size control mechanism in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii.

- Used a data-mining strategy to identify highly expressed genes in Chlamydomonas whose flanking sequences were tested for the ability to drive heterologous nuclear transgene expression.
- Identified a sizer protein, CDKG1, that acts through the retinoblastoma tumor suppressor pathway as a D-cyclin-dependent RB kinase to regulate mitotic counting in Chlamydomonas.
- Characterized a sizer protein TNY1, which modulates cell-size homeostasis through cell-cycle-controlled synthesis and dosage-dependent repression of the size activator CDKG1.
- Measured the nuclear:cell volume ratio in wild-type Chlamydomonas and size mutants throughout the multiple fission cell cycle using fluorescence microscopy.
- Established stochastic models for growth and division to elucidate the functions of both commitment and mitotic sizers in the size homeostasis of Chlamydomonas.

Undergraduate Research

2010.9 - 2012.5

Dr. Vitaly Citovsky's lab. Dept. of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, **Stony Brook University Thesis: Improve the transgene efficiency in** *Lemnaceae lemna gibba*.

- Compared pathogenic interactions between agrobacterium and E.coli on Solanum lycopersicum.
- Improved transgene method on Lemnaceae (increased transgene efficiency from 20% to 80%), based on floral
 dip method on Arabidopsis thaliana (Cooperated with Dr. Jörg Schwender's lab at Brookhaven National
 Laboratory, NY).

MANUSCRIPTS

Scientific Journal Articles

- [1] (In prepration for *Current Biology*) **Liu, D.**, García, C., Singh A., and Umen, J.G. Stochastic hybrid system approach to elucidate a cellular counting and sizing mechanism in Chlamydomonas.
- [2] (In prepration for the *Plant Cell*) **Liu, D.,** Lopez-Paz, C., Li, Y., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway.
- [3] (In prepration for *Plos One*) **Liu, D.** and Umen, J.G. Testing the constancy of the nuclear: cell volume ratio in Chlamydomonas.
- [4] Lopez-Paz, C.*, **Liu, D.*,** Geng, S., and Umen, J.G. (2017). Identification of Chlamydomonas reinhardtii endogenous genic flanking sequences for improved transgene expression. *The Plant Journal:* for cell and molecular biology 92, 1232-1244. (*co-first author)
- [5] Li, Y.*, **Liu, D.***, Lopez-Paz, C., Olson, B.J., and Umen, J.G. (2016). A new class of cyclin dependent kinase in Chlamydomonas is required for coupling cell size to cell division. *eLife* 5:e10767 (*co-first author)
- [6] (Review) Yu, Y., You, L., **Liu, D.,** Hollinshead, W., Tang, Y.J., and Zhang, F. (2013). Development of Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803 as a phototrophic cell factory. *Marine drugs* 11, 2894-2916.

Sourcebook Chapter

[1] The Chlamydomonas Sourcebook, 3rd Edition

2022, Elsevier

Volumes 1 - Introduction to Chlamydomonas and Its Laboratory Use Chapter 6 - Cell Cyle and Circadian Rhythm

James Umen and Dianyi Liu

Published Translations of Books

[1] Happier at Home, Chinese Edition 《幸福断舍离》 ISBN-9787508685977 July 2018, CITIC Publishing Group

中信出版集团

The book is a mandarin Chinese Edition translated by me from Gretchen Rubin's *New York Times* best-seller *Happier at Home*.

[2] Ten Billion Tomorrows, Chinese Edition 《100 亿个明天》

Jun 2017, CITIC Publishing Group

ISBN-9787508675886

中信出版集团

The book is a mandarin Chinese Edition translated by me from Brian Clegg's science fiction *Ten Billion Tomorrows:* How Science Fiction Technology Became Reality and Shapes the Future.

PEER REVIEW EXPERIENCES

- Independent Peer Review: Journal of Evolutionary Biology, PeerJ
- Facilitated Peer Review: Science, The Plant Cell, Plos Genetics, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences

SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS & AWARDS

2021 American Society for Cell Biology (ASCB) and European Molecular Biology Organization (EMBO)

2021.6

Workshop on Cell Size and Growth Regulation

- ★ Speaker by the ASCB/EMBO Workshop Program Committee (talk [1])
- [1] Talk: **Liu, D.,** Vargas-García, C., Singh, A., and Umen, J.G. Elucidating the mitotic sizer in the multiple fission alga *Chlamydomonas reinhardtii*

The 2020 joint meeting of the American Society for Cell Biology (**ASCB**) and European Molecular Biology 2020.12 Organization (**EMBO**) vitual meeting

- [2] Poster and video presentation: **Liu, D.**, Lopez-Paz, C., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway
- [3] Poster and video presentation: **Liu, D.**, Vargas-García, C., Singh, A., and Umen, J. G. Elucidating the mitotic sizer in the multiple fission alga *Chlamydomonas reinhardtii*

The Plant Cell Atlas, Carnegie Institution for Science, Stanford, CA

2020.5

- **★ Travel Award** by the **Plant Cell Atlas** for the in-person workshops
- **★ Scribe** for all the virtual sessions
- ★ Consortium Author for the report of the 1st Plant Cell Atlas Workshop

The 2019 joint meeting of the American Society for Cell Biology (**ASCB**) and European Molecular Biology 2019.12 Organization (**EMBO**), Washington DC

- ★ Participant of **Green Fluorescent Protein Image and Video Contest** "Hatchlings," fearturing the whole *in vivo* hatching process of *Chlamydomonas reinhardtii* by a ZEISS Elyra 7 with Apotome super-resolution microscopy in 3D Leap-Mode.
- [4] Poster: **Liu, D**., Lopez-Paz, C., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway
- [5] Poster: **Liu, D.**, Vargas-García, C., Singh, A., and Umen, J. G. Modeling stochastic behavior of size control in the multiple fission cell cycle of Chlamydomonas

ASPB (American Society of Plant Biologists) Plant Biology 2019, San Jose, CA

2019.8

- ★ ASPB Travel Grant by ASPB Plant Biology 2019
- ★ Concurrent Symposium Speaker by the ASPB Program Committee (talk [6])

- [6] Talk: **Liu, D**., Lopez-Paz, C., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway
- [7] Poster: **Liu, D.** and Umen, J.G. Testing the constancy of the nuclear: cell volume ratio in wild type and cell-size mutants of Chlamydomonas.
- [8] Poster: **Liu, D.** and Umen, J.G. Stochastic hybrid system approach to elucidate a cellular counting and sizing mechanism in Chlamydomonas.
- [9] Poster: **Liu, D**., Lopez-Paz, C., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway

The 18th Int'l Conference on the Cell and Molecular Biology of Chlamydomonas, Washington DC

2018.6

- ★ Travel Award by the Committee for Scientific Training and Mentoring at the Danforth Plant Science Center [10] Poster: Liu, D., Lopez-Paz, C., Geng, S., and Umen, J.G. Identification of Chlamydomonas reinhardtii endogenous genic flanking sequences for improved transgene expression.
- [11] Poster: **Liu, D.**, Lopez-Paz, C., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway

2018 Danforth Plant Science Center Annual Retreat, Potosi, MO

2018.5

- ★ Best Talk Award by the Danforth Plant Science Center Retreat Committee (talk [12])
- [12] Talk: **Liu, D.**, Lopez-Paz, C., and Umen, J.G. A heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP)-like protein in Chlamydomonas functions as a cell-cycle repressor in the retinoblastoma cell-size control pathway

The 4th Int'l Volvox Conference, St. Louis, MO

2017.8

- ★ Designed the conference logo and giveaways
- ★ Volunteered at the registration desk

The 17th Int'l Conference on the Cell and Molecular Biology of Chlamydomonas, Kyoto, Japan

2016.6

- ★ Travel Award by the Committee for Scientific Training and Mentoring at the Danforth Plant Science Center
- ★ Best Poster Award by the 17th Int'l Conference on the Cell and Molecular Biology of Chlamydomonas (poster [14]).
- [13] Poster: **Liu, D.**, Li, Y., Lopez-Paz, C., Olson, B.J., and Umen, J.G. A new class of cyclin dependent kinase in Chlamydomonas is required for coupling cell size to cell division.
- [14] Poster: **Liu, D**.and Umen, J.G. Testing the constancy of the nuclear : cell volume ratio in wild type and cell-size mutants of Chlamydomonas.

2016 Danforth Plant Science Center Annual Retreat, Grafton, IL

2016.5

- ★ Best Talk Award by the Danforth Plant Science Center Retreat Committee (talk [15]).
- [15] Talk: **Liu, D.**, Li, Y., Lopez-Paz, C., Olson, B.J., and Umen, J.G. A new class of cyclin dependent kinase in Chlamydomonas is required for coupling cell size to cell division.
- [16] Poster: **Liu, D.**, Li, Y., Lopez-Paz, C., Olson, B.J., and Umen, J.G. A new class of cyclin dependent kinase in Chlamydomonas is required for coupling cell size to cell division.

The 16th Int'l Conference on the Cell and Molecular Biology of Chlamydomonas, Pacific Groves, CA

2014.6

★ Travel Award by the **Genetics Society of America**

[17] Poster: **Liu, D**., Li, Y., Lopez-Paz, C., Olson, B.J., and Umen, J.G. A new class of cyclin dependent kinase in Chlamydomonas is required for coupling cell size to cell division.

INVITED TALKS AND WORKSHOPS

Chinese University of Hong Kong (Hong Kong), hosted by Dr. XiaoHong ZHUANG

2019. 11

- Talk: The conserved retinoblastoma tumor suppressor pathway controls cell size in Chlamydomonas
- Workshop: An introduction of the Volvocine algae family, from the evolution of the multicellularity to the multiple fission cell cycle
- Hands-on in lab: Immunofluorescence microscopy to detect protein of interest in Chlamydomonas.

Westlake University (Zhejiang, China), hosted by Dr. XiaoBo LI

2019.11

Talk: The conserved retinoblastoma tumor suppressor pathway controls cell size in Chlamydomonas

• **Hands-on in lab:** [1] Protein extraction and co-immunoprecipitation in Chlamydomonas. [2] Sexual mating in Chlamydomonas.

INTERNSHIPS

copper wire, steel nails, and cooking vinegar.

Bayer CropScience LLC, Chesterfield. MO. Summer 2022 Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, China Summer 2011 • Analyzed the transcriptome of an anti-freeze protein in tobacco *Nicotiana benthamiana*. National Institute of Metrology, Beijing, China Summer 2010 (Analytical Chemistry Department) Operated liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry. **EDUCATION AND OUTREACH ACTIVITIES** California College of the Arts, CA 2022.2 FASHN-3200-2- Investigative Studio: Biodesign • **Guest lecturer** for undergraduate art-major students Designed and presented "Why do we care about algae?" explaining (1) algae hunting, (2) algae culturing, (3) algae in daily lives, and (4) general algae research topics. The Institute for School Partnership at Washington University in St. Louis, MO 2020.7 Educ. 6008.51 - Teaching the Process of Scientific Investigation • **Guest lecturer** on a virtual panel for K-8 science teachers. Designed and presented "Efficient Interpretation of Science," explaining (1) designing STEM projects for students, (2) introducing science to a general audience, and (3) broadcasting science outside of academic settings. South City Academy STEAM Night, Confluence Charter Schools, MO 2020.2 Designed and led the project "Science in Plants." **Representative** of the Danforth Plant Science Center Booth. Taught pre-K to 8th grades (~ 840 students) about (1) differences between plants and animals, (2) photosynthesis and C3, C4, and CAM plants. DDPSC Students Field Trips for Ladue Horton Watkins High School, Ladue School District, MO 2019.12 Led project "Discover Volvox Development." Taught 10th grade from (8 sessions, ~60 students) about evolution and germ-somatic cell differentiation by characterizing wild type and developmental mutants of Volvox under dissecting microscope. STEM DAY at Meadows Elementary, Riverview Gardens School District, MO 2019.3 Led project "Strawberry DNA Extraction." Taught 5th grade (7 sessions, ~100 students) about DNA by isolating DNA from frozen strawberries using soap, salt, and isopropyl-alcohol. Raspberry Pi Jam at Danforth Plant Science Center 2019.1 Volunteered at the Snap Circuit booth. STEM DAY at Marvin Elementary School, Ritenour School District, MO 2018.5 Led project "Ice Tray Battery." Taught 1st grade (7 sessions, ~80 students) about electric circuit by lighting LED lights using ice tray,

2018.1

- Led project "Rainbow in a Jar."
- Taught pre-K (8 sessions, ~80 students) about density by making a rainbow cocktail in a glass jar using soap, water, cooking oil, and colored isopropyl-alcohol.

Raspberry Pi Jam at Danforth Plant Science Center

Volunteered at the Soldering booth.

CAREER DEVELOPMENT ACTIVITIES

❖ Mentor of 1st year rotation PhD student at Washington University
 ❖ Member of the American Society for Cell Biology (ASCB)
 Spring 2022, Spring 2019
 2019.7-present

❖ THREE MINUTE THESIS (3MT®) Workshop. Donald Danforth Plant Science Center.

2019.7

★ Final round competitor in science communication event titled "Science Impacting Society: Lightning Talks" for a broad public audience of 100+

❖ Member of the American Society of Plant Biologists (ASPB)
 Ż Teaching Assistant of BIOL2013 Genetics laboratory, University of Missouri, St. Louis
 ❖ Attendee of Confocal Microscopy Workshop. Donald Danforth Plant Science Center.
 ❖ Teaching Assistant of BIO320 Genetics, Stony Brook University

2019.1-present
Spring 2018
Spring 2014
Spring 2014

❖ Member of Undergraduate Biochemistry Society, Stony Brook University
2010.10 – 2012.5

CONTRACTING WORK AND SIDE PROJECTS

❖ Contractor at Pop Science official account *Principia1687* 原理

2021.1-2021.12

- Writer/Editor/Proposal Designer.
- Participated in 10+ pop science articles.
- Received 200K+ combined views on WeChat.
- ❖ English Subtitle Translator for documentaries by Director Ryo Takeuchi 竹内亮

2020.6-present

- Translated dialogues and voice-over originally in Chinese or Japanese into English.
- Participated in 5+ documentaries including Long Time No See, Wuhan (2020), Beyond the Mountain (2021), and Two-Sided the Olympics: TOKYO 2020 DIARY (2021).
- Received 10M+ combined views on YouTube.

OTHER RESPONSIBILITIES AND ACTIVITIES

.	 Staff lecturer at St. Louis Modern Chinese School Designed syllabus and taught Chinese-as-the-Second-Language to adult English-speakers. Substitute teacher for 7th grade Chinese. Primary teacher at 2021 Chinese Cultural Immersion Youth Summer Camp by Associations of Chinese-Americans. Teacher representative/Speaker at the world-wide online graduation ceremony. 	2021.6 – present 2022 Fall 2022 Spring 2021 Summer
*	 Member of Japan America Society Women's Association of St. Louis (JASWA). Board Member. Communication Coordinator to set up Zoom meetings and arrange/organize venues. 	2018.12-present 2019.12-present 2022.1-present

Editor of the bi-monthly English-Japanese bi-lingual JASWA newsletter.
 Editor of the annual JASWA directory.
 2019.10-2021.12
 2019.10-2021.12

Hospitality Assistant. Sent crafts, hand-made cards, and flowers to members.
 2019.10-2020.3

*	Member of Japanese Traditional Dance Group Tohzan-ryu (日本舞踊 - 東山流)	2019.9-present
	• Solo stage performance O-getsu-sama (お月様) at the Japanese Festival in St. Louis	
*	Member of St. Louis Bon Odori Group (盆踊り)	2017.5-present
	 Performed at the St. Louis Japanese Festival for four years 	
	 Performed at cultural events at Lindenwold University and Maryville University 	
*	Completion of a Half Marathon. Go! St. Louis 2018	2018.4
*	Certificate of Completion in Bartending/Mixology, the Bartending Institute of St. Louis	2017.6
*	Official Volunteer for road guidance at 2008 Beijing Summer Olympic Games	2008.8